<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/contacts.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Status</title>

    <section title="Running The Examples">

      <p>The script files <tt>example.sh</tt> and <tt>example.bat</tt> can
         be used to run the provided examples. The first argument is the example
         package name. For example, to build and run the JDO example:
<pre>
  build.sh examples
  test.sh jdo odmg
</pre>
      </p>

    </section>

    <section title="Castor JDO">

      <p>The JDO sample will test persistence between a set of Java classes
         (Product, ProductGroup, ProductInventory) and a known SQL schema.
         You can use the <tt>create.sql</tt> file to generate the database schema
         for the purpose of this test.</p>

      <p>The mapping between the Java objects and SQL schema is described in
         the file <tt>mapping.xml</tt>. The JDBC connection to use is describes
         in the file <tt>database.xml</tt>. The provided file uses PostgreSQL as
         the database server and JDBC driver, you can modify this file for your database
         server and use any JDBC 1.0 or 2.0 driver.</p>

      <p>The database information and mapping are automatically read from the
         JDO example directory, there is no need to provide any parameters on
         the command line.</p>

      <p>The performance test uses the ODMG engine as well as direct JDBC
         access. You must provide the JDBC URI and class name to use for
         this test on the command line.</p>

      <p>Usage:
<pre><![CDATA[
  test.sh jdo [mapping|odmg|perf <driver-class> <jdbc-uri>]

  mapping  Reads the Java/SQL mapping from the mapping files and
           displays the SQL statements used by the engine

  odmg     Performs a persistence test using the ODMG API
           Will attempt to query, deleter and create product,
           group and computer objects in the database

  perf     Performs a performance test comparing direct JDBC
           query performance with ODMG query performance.
           Requires the JDBC driver class name and JDBC URI
           to be specified.
]]></pre>
         For example:
<pre><![CDATA[
  test.sh jdo odmg
  test.sh jdo perf postgresql.Driver "jdbc:postgresql:test?user=test&password=test"
]]></pre>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="Castor DSML">

      <p>Do not run this sample against a production LDAP server unless you
         are sure it will not affect the information in your directory!</p>

      <p>The DSML sample will attempt to import the supplied directory
         information from the test.xml file using the import policy described
         in the <tt>import.xml</tt>. file. It will then run a search against the
         LDAP server using the search criteria in the search.xml file and dump it
         to the console.</p>

      <p>You must modify <tt>search.xml</tt>, <tt>import.xml</tt> and
         <tt>test.xml</tt> and adapt them to your LDAP directory structure.
         The default files assumes the root directory dc=exoffice,dc=com and
         includes some sample LDAP entries.</p>

      <p>Usage:
<pre><![CDATA[
  test.sh dsml [jndi|mozilla] <host> <root-dn> <root-pwd>

  jndi|mozilla  Selects whether to use the JNDI or Mozilla Directory
	        SDK implementations
  host          The LDAP host name (port number is optional)
  rood-dn       The root DN used for authenticating when importing
  root-pwd      The root password used for authenticating when importing
]]></pre>
         For example:
<pre><![CDATA[
  test.sh dsml mozilla ldap.exoffice.org dc=exoffice,dc=com secret
]]></pre>
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
