<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/lists.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Castor Mailing Lists</title>
    <header>
    </header>
    <section title="Mailing Lists">

      <p><b>Note:</b> Presently we are hosting three mailing lists. Traffic is not too high,
         so if you are interested in keeping up to date with new releases, or have problems,
         questions or feedback please <a href="lists.xml">subscribe
         to the appropriate list</a>.
      </p>




      <section title="castor-user">
         <p><b>castor-user</b>  - <font color="red">NEW!</font></p>
         <p>Moderate volume expected (possibly more than 15 messages a day) - mailing list dedicated
            to the users of Castor.</p>

         <p><mailing-list name="castor-user" description="The Castor User's Mailing List"
                       server="exolab.org" manager="minimalist"/>

            <p>
                <b>Note:</b> please familiarize yourself with the <a href="#Guidelines">guidelines</a>
                before posting to the list.
            </p>

            <b>Archives:</b>
            <p><b>Note:</b> There may be a delay of one (1) or two (2) days for messages
              to be archived at that site.</p>
            <ul> - The following archive was just set up and may not yet be available at mail-archive.com.
               <li><url>http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-user%40exolab.org</url></li>
            </ul>
         </p>
      </section>

      <section title="castor-dev">
         <p><b>castor-dev</b></p>
         <p>Moderate volume (possibly more than 15 messages a day) mailing list dedicated
            to the developers of Castor.</p>

         <p><mailing-list name="castor-dev" description="The Castor Developer's Mailing List"
                       server="exolab.org" manager="minimalist"/>

            <p>
                <b>Note:</b> please familiarize yourself with the <a href="#Guidelines">guidelines</a>
                before posting to the list.
            </p>

            <b>Archives:</b>
            <p><b>Note:</b> There may be a delay of one (1) or two (2) days for messages
              to be archived at that site.</p>

            <ul>
               <li><url>http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=castor-dev</url></li>
               <li><url>http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-dev%40exolab.org</url></li>
               <li><url>http://hypermail.linklord.com/castor-dev/</url></li>
            </ul>
         </p>
      </section>

      <section title="castor-announce">
         <p><b>castor-announce</b></p>
         <p>Low volume (possibly more than 1 message per week)
            mailing list for special announcements about Castor, such as
            new releases.
         </p>

         <p><mailing-list name="castor-announce" description="The Castor Announcement Mailing List"
                       server="exolab.org" manager="minimalist"/></p>
       </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Guidelines">
    <p>
    The following are some general "common-sense" guidelines for using the
    mailing lists:</p>

    <p>
    Most people are already following these guidelines. To those people, we
    thank you. For those of you who are not ... please read carefully.

    <ol>

       <li><p>Please be kind and respectful to your fellow castor users.</p></li>

       <li><p>Please refrain from using words and phrases like URGENT, IMPORTANT,
           MY WIFE WILL LEAVE ME IF YOU DO NOT RESPOND, etc, in the subject line
           of your postings. Or even in the body of the message for that matter.</p>

           <p>You may think that things which are URGENT, or IMPORTANT to you,
           are just as urgent and important to everyone else reading this
           list. You'd be surprised at just how wrong an assumption like
           that can be.</p></li>

       <li><p>Please use meaningful subject lines. "Newbie Question",
           is not meaningful what-so-ever.</p></li>

       <li><p>Please provide necessary information, where applicable.
           Statements like, "I receive a NullPointerException when
           using Castor, what's up with that?", are not very helpful,
           add unnecessary traffic on the list, and will probably
           never get an answer.</p></li>

       <li><p>As a follow on to #3, when submitting examples, please try
           to submit the smallest possible example which demonstrates
           the problem. Short examples are easier to follow and will
           get quicker responses from developers or other users than
           long examples with lots of extraneous code/data.</p></li>

       <li><p>Please read the documentation before posting. It doesn't take
           long and it will save us valuable time from having to answer
           questions that are already covered in the docs.</p></li>

       <li><p>Please check the mail archives before posting. Many questions
           on this list have already been answered before.</p></li>

       <li><p>Please refrain from posting confidential information. Once an
           e-mail is sent to the list, it goes out to all subscribers,
           including archive engines. We cannot remove or delete messages
           sent to the list. Once sent they are available for the public
           to see. If you are unsure about what is confidential or not,
           check with your manager, supervisor, or the person in charge
           at your company.</p></li>


       <li><p>If you are going on vacation. Please enjoy yourself. We
           really want you to have fun and get some much needed
           rest and relaxation. With that being said and to be
           perfectly honest none of us really want to receive your
           automated vacation responses. So please either add a filter
           to your vacation response so it doesn't get sent to the
           list or users posting to the list, or simply remove yourself
           from the list before you go, and add yourself back when
           you return.</p></li>

       <li><p>Please refrain from sending emails to this mailing list formatted
           as text/html.</p></li>

    </ol>
    </p>


    </section>

     <section title="A note about HTML formatted e-mail">
       <p>
       As stated in the guildelines above (see #10), please <b>refrain</b> from sending email to
       these mailing lists formatted as <b>'text/html'</b> under all circumstances.
       </p>
       <p>
       Amongst other things, it complicates life for users not working on
       Windows and decreases usability of the mailing list archives, as it
       prevents text searches from returning useful results.
       </p>
       <p>
       Additional information why we consider HTML emails to be avoided can be
       found <a href="http://www.birdhouse.org/etc/evilmail.html">here</a>.
       </p>
     </section>

  </body>
</document>
